Finding Aid for the Albert Boime Papers LSC.1834
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 3: Research materials, 1941-2008
  - Social Issues, 1986-2005
    - Black male New York, ca. 1994 (Box 48, Folder 5)
      Paper and exhibition brochures on art work and representations of black masculinity.
    - Japanese American, 1989-1990, 2001 (Box 48, Folder 6)
      Clippings, student paper "My Arizona: Isamu Noguchi and the Incarceration of Japanese-Americans During World War II" by Amy Lyford of Boston University, and e-mail correspondence.
    - Chinese American, ca. 1995-1996 (Box 48, Folder 7)
      Copies of essays by Paul Von Blum and Anthony Lee regarding Chinese Americans.
    - Diaspora issues, 1995-1996 (Box 48, Folder 8)
      Exhibition Outline from Neery Melkonian for "Between Heaven and Hell: Contemporary Art from the Middle Eastern Diaspora" and notes.
    - University of Washington workshop, 1991 (Box 48, Folder 9)
      Notes, annotated photocopies, flyers, correspondence regarding Boime's "Race, Gender and Class" workshop at the University of Washington, and project descriptions from students in the class that Boime visited at U of W.
    - Stereotypes, 1991-1992 (Box 48, Folder 10)
      Bibliography and outline for paper on cartoons and stereotypical representations of Irish immigrants, paper on unusual physical features, and outline and bibliography for "Issues of Ethnicity, Representation, and Gender in Nineteenth Century American Popular Art" by Stacy Kamehiro.
    - Art History 202: Ethnographic Studies of Art, ca. 1990 (Box 49, Folder 1)
      Book outline/proposal for "Form and Function of Bidjogo Shrine Sculpture" (authorship unclear), "Aesthetics and Semiotics: New Visions and New Voices" conference materials, and Art History 202 syllabus.
    - Feminism II, 1992 (Box 49, Folder 2)
      Women's Studies pamphlet, paper "Masculinity in Crisis" by Amy Kesselhaut, Dictionary of Women Artists, correspondence, and copy of UCLArt Interview (possibly with Lucy R. Lippard).
    - Modernism and Feminism, 1992 (Box 49, Folder 3)
      Syllabus and readings for course "Women and Art in Contemporary United States" led by Sondra Hale. Folder also includes articles.
    - Gay and lesbian, 1992 (Box 49, Folder 4)
      Correspondence and publication "Studies in Homosexuality" featuring anthology of scholarly articles.
    - Gay and racial, ca. 1999 (Box 49, Folder 5)
      Notes, article "Homoeroticism and the Quest for Originality in Girodet's Revolt at Cairo (1810)," and foldout poster for exhibition "Sex, Lies, and Stereotypes: Posters on Sexism and Homophobia" by the Center for the Study of Political Graphics.
    - Trompe L'Oeil painting, 1989 (Box 49, Folder 6)
      Exhibition brochure for "Yani: The Brush of Innocence" by the Smithsonian Institution, papers on Trompe L'Oeil painting by David Lubin for several conferences, and pages from unidentified drafts (topics include Winckelmann).
    - Miscellaneous social issues, 1989 (Box 49, Folder 7)
      Notes, brochure on "The Papers of African American Artists," correspondence, invoices, photocopies, and Washington DC maps.
    - AIDS, 1989 (Box 49, Folder 8)
      Publication regarding The Names Project AIDS Memorial Quilt in Washington DC, catalog for exhibition "Images & Words: Artists Respond to AIDS," and draft of "The AIDS Memorial Quilt: Mourning, Activism, and the Politics of Sentimentality" by Richard Iosty.
    - Angels from the Vatican, 1997 (Box 49, Folder 9)
      Exhibition packet for Angels from the Vatican exhibit at the Hammer Museum (sponsored by the Chrysler Corporation).
    - Islam, ca. 1991 (Box 49, Folder 10)
      Flyers, newsletters, and political publications.
    - Islam, 1998 (Box 49, Folder 11)
      Saudi Arabia brochures, pamphlet "A Parent's Guide to Religion in the Public Schools," and resource manual from Parent Education Outreach "Islamic Awareness Conference."
    - Religion, ca. 1998 (Box 49, Folder 12)
      Photocopied article on Afrocuban rites and rituals in Cuba and paper by Jacques Derrida "Avowing--The Impossible: 'Returns,' Repentance and Reconciliation."
    - Southwest crypto-Jews, undated (Box 49, Folder 13)
      Photocopied article "The Secret Legacy of Christopher Columbus in the Southwest."
    - Jews and Israel (1 of 2), 1996-1998, 2000 (Box 49, Folder 14)
      Articles, working paper from SUNY Stony brook by Richard Williams on "Stereotype Research: A Sociological Analysis (1918-1970)," typed memoir of Holocaust survivor, clippings, notes, copies of papers on Jewish identity, conference programs, and e-mail correspondence (general theme of perspectives on Israeli-Palestinian conflict).
    - Jews and Israel (2 of 2), 1996-1998, 2000 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Transnational, undated (Box 50, Folder 2)
      Paper by George Baker "Response to Okwui Enwezor, 'Mega-Exhibitions and the Antinomies of a Transnational Global Form.'"
    - India, ca. 1994-1995 (Box 50, Folder 3)
      Exhibition brochure for LACMA exhibition on Jain Art from India and project description by Debashish Banerji "Locating Abanindranath Tagore: Local, National and Transnational Concerns in a Turn-of-the-Century Indian Artist."
    - Iraq, 2003 (Box 50, Folder 4)
      Clippings and issue of magazine "Nonviolent Activist" from March-April 2003. All items are related to U.S. intervention in Iraq.
    - Gulf War, 1991 (Box 50, Folder 5)
      Program from day of alternative education on Gulf War, clippings, and flyers.
    - Vietnam, undated (Box 50, Folder 6)
      Publication "Lessons of the Vietnam War."
    - Bosnia, etc., 1996 (Box 50, Folder 7)
      Paper "The New Apartheid" by Omer Ale Suleimanagich and issue of The Washington Spectator from June 15, 1996.
    - The Sixties, undated (Box 50, Folder 8)
      Note and paper by Claudia Mesch entitled "Marcuse and the End of the '60s"
    - Social history, ca. 1989 (Box 50, Folder 9)
      Notes, correspondence, article photocopy, and draft of talk regarding homelessness.
  - Academies, 1968-1998
    Boime's research on art academies and academic painting, likely for his publication "Towards a Theory of the Academy," among others. The subseries includes several drafts and papers for an anthology that Boime compiled on the Academy. Other materials include correspondence with specific academies, informational materials about their programs, and notes. This subseries is arranged topically beginning with drafts and general academy research, and ending with research on specific academies.
    - Academies (Box 139, Folder 4)
    - Vrije Academie, ca. 1970 (Box 139, Folder 5)
      Mailings from Vrije Academie in the Hague. Materials in Dutch.
    - Loose materials, 1980-1982 (Box 139, Folder 6)
      Small notebook, maps, and New York Drawing Association brochures.
    - Loose materials, 1960-1972 (Box 139, Folder 7)
      Correspondence, mailings from art academies, and notes. Folder also includes small blue book: Art as a Function of Government (possibly an exam or lecture notes), information regarding the Royal Swedish Academy, syllabus from Durban, University of Canterbury course material and student work samples, and Warburg Institute booklet. Some materials in German and Dutch.
    - Academy papers, 1983-1984 (Box 50, Folder 10)
      Notes and correspondence. Folder also includes a copy of draft by Clark V. Poling "Kandinsky's Analytical Drawing Class at the Bauhaus," draft by Bruce Laughton "The Slade School: An Anti-Academic Academy," draft by Karen-edis Barzman "Institutionalizing Albertian Principles of Education," draft by Judith Testa "A Graduate of the 'Ghent-Bruges School': Simon Bening's Acquisition and Uses of Traditional Compositions," and draft of "Towards a Theory of the Academy."
    - Academy papers, undated (Box 50, Folder 11)
      Drafts of papers and table of contents for anthology on the Academy.
    - Academy - essay #1, undated (Box 50, Folder 12)
      Notes and pages from draft of "Towards a Theory of the Academy."
    - Royal Academy - draft, undated (Box 50, Folder 13)
      Miscellaneous pages from draft on Royal Academy.
    - Academy - draft, undated (Box 50, Folder 14)
      Draft of "Towards a Theory of the Academy."
    - Chapter IV: Pedagogical Reform, undated (Box 51, Folder 1)
      Draft of "Pedagogical Reform" with some edits.
    - Reforms of 1863, undated (Box 51, Folder 2)
      Draft of "The Reforms of 1863."
    - 1863 additions, undated (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Prix de Rome, undated (Box 51, Folder 4)
      Paper with subheading "The Minor Competitions."
    - Prix de Rome, undated (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Oil sketches, undated (Box 51, Folder 6)
      Notes and draft of "Political Signification and Ambiguity in the Oil Sketch" with edits. Folder also includes a photo of Boime.
    - Oil sketches, ca. 1998 (Box 51, Folder 7)
      Several drafts of "Political Signification and Ambiguity in the Oil Sketch" with some edits.
    - Academy notes and drafts (1 of 5), undated (Box 51, Folder 8)
      Notes, drafts, and unidentified publications relating to Boime's work on Academies.
    - Academy notes and drafts (2 of 5), undated (Box 51, Folder 9)
    - Academy notes and drafts (3 of 5), undated (Box 51, Folder 10)
    - Academy notes and drafts (4 of 5), undated (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Academy notes and drafts (5 of 5), undated (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Academy anthology (1 of 3), ca. 1974 (Box 52, Folder 3)
      Drafts of chapters for an anthology about the Academy and art. Folder includes correspondence from the publisher and lecture notes. Authors include LeGrace Benson, Peg Weiss, Alessandra Comini, Dorathea K Beard, Jack Cowart, Alfonz Lengyel, Aidron Duckworth, Henri Dorra, Manuela Hoelterhoff, Eric Cameron, and Carl Goldstein.
    - Academy anthology (2 of 3), ca. 1974 (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Academy anthology (3 of 3), ca. 1974 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Drafts of academy papers, undated (Box 52, Folder 6)
      Draft of paper entitled "Official Art: Crystallization and History, The Typical Official Career (Beginning), The Concepts of 'Official' and 'Academic.'"
    - Academies, 1970 (Box 53, Folder 1)
      Correspondence from art academies around the world including Université Laval (Quebec), Royal College of Art, Academie van Beeldende Kunsten Rotterdam, école Supérieure des Beaux-Arts d'Athénes, Jan Van Eyck Academie, Accademia di Belle Arti - Firenze, Banaras Hindu University, College for Advanced Technical Education, école Nationale des Beaux-Arts de Dijon, College of Chinese Culture, Instituto Statale D'Arte Di Bologna, and School of Arts Trivandrum. Some materials in Italian and French.
    - Academies, bulk 1978, 1973-1975 (Box 53, Folder 2)
      Notes, photocopies, correspondence (correspondents include Alastair Granville-Jackson), Italian and Spanish pamphlets about art academies, and draft "Academies of Art." Some materials in French.
    - Academies, 1970s-1980s (Box 53, Folder 3)
      Correspondence, notes, articles, bibliography of Academy of San Carlos, draft of "History without Roots: The Birth and Early Growth of American Art Institutions" by Carrie Rebora, and photographic negatives. Some materials in Italian.
    - Academies, bulk 1979, 1993 (Box 53, Folder 4)
      Correspondence from American Academy in Rome, notes, copy of "To Copy to Create: The Louvre's Bicentennial" by Wayne Andersen, and copy of Art Bulletin, 58, March 1975. Folder also includes a draft of "Towards a Theory of the Academy" with some edits and a draft of "Two Documents for the Roman Academy of Saint Luke."
    - Academies, 1968-1974, 1982-1983 (Box 53, Folder 5)
      Correspondence and materials regarding academies and study in the Netherlands, Great Britain, Italy, and New York. Some materials in German and French.
    - Academies, 1970, 1982-1984 (Box 53, Folder 6)
      Correspondence, notes, and materials from Kyoto College of Fine Arts, Royal Swedish Academy of Fine Arts, and the New York Drawing Association. Some materials in German.
    - Academies - miscellaneous, 1974-1976, 1978 (Box 53, Folder 7)
      Correspondence (correspondents include William Dubin), illustration lists, drawings, copy of Educational Statistics of the Republic of China, and academy photographs. Folder also includes copy of paper by Stephanie R. Cassidy "Reconstructing the Artist: The Rise of the Art Students League of New York, 1875-1920" and a Louvre catalog.
    - Academies - miscellaneous, 1974, 1986 (Box 53, Folder 8)
      Images from Grand Central Art Gallery, photographic negatives and associated slide list of Matisse drawings, and notes.
    - Academies - miscellaneous, 1972-1975, 1994-1996 (Box 54, Folder 1)
      Articles, photocopies, correspondence, copy of Systemanalyse Akademie München: Verfassungsanalyse, newsletter, and programs about drawing. Some materials in German.
    - The cultural politics of the art academy, 1993 (Box 54, Folder 2)
      Correspondence and draft of "The Cultural Politics of the Art Academy" (correspondents include Joel Reed).
    - Novack - utopia, undated (Box 54, Folder 3)
      Draft of "Art from Nowhere: The Academy in Utopia" with some edits.
    - Novack - academy, 2003-2004 (Box 54, Folder 4)
      Annotated photocopies, notes, correspondence regarding program "Age of Projects: Changing and Improving the Arts, Literature, and Life during the Long Eighteenth Century, 1660-1820" coordinated by Maximillian Novack, and drafts of "Art from Nowhere: The Academy in Utopia" with edits.
    - Academy notes, undated (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Academy, 1968, 1970 (Box 54, Folder 6)
      Correspondence, notes, paper by Robin Messick "Aspects of Indian Art Under British Rule," and Art Academy of Cincinnati history and timeline.
    - Academies: comparison, undated (Box 54, Folder 7)
      Draft of "French Academic Training and Art Education in Korea."
    - Seoul National University, 1998 (Box 54, Folder 8)
      Draft of "French Academic Training and Art Education in Korea" with some edits, correspondence, course materials, and notes.
    - Materials from New York Academy of Art, undated (Box 54, Folder 9)
      Articles and papers.
    - New York Drawing Association, 1981 (Box 55, Folder 1)
      Correspondence, photocopies (topics include murals), informational materials for NY Drawing Association (faculty lists, maps, tuition and course information), and copies of press clippings.
    - Academie Julian Project, 1981-1982, 1986 (Box 55, Folder 2)
      Slides and slide notes on works by Oscar Fehrer, notes, and correspondence with Catherine Fehrer. Folder also includes draft of "The Academie Julian and the Marketing of Art" and draft of "The Academie Julian: A Successful Enterprise of the Third Republic."
    - Cincinnati, 1973-1974 (Box 55, Folder 3)
      Correspondence, letter from Cincinnati Art Museum on Art Academy of Cincinnati, student paper by Richard S. Schneiderman, and 2 student papers by Mel Lader.
    - Cincinnati Academy, undated (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - English Art Institutes, undated (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - Canada Academy, undated (Box 55, Folder 6)
    - Henry Few Smith - Dusseldorf Academy, undated (Box 55, Folder 7)
      Photocopies and article "Henry Few Smith, Philadelphia Artist, 1821-1846" by Maurice Browning Cramer (annotated by Boime). Folder also includes annotated copies of letters from and to Henry.
    - The Ecole at Rome (before 1863), undated (Box 55, Folder 8)
      Draft of paper titled "The Ecole at Rome" (unclear authorship) with corrections throughout.
    - Drawing forum, undated (Box 55, Folder 9)
    - Bauhaus, 1974 (Box 55, Folder 10)
      Correspondence and writings by Clark V. Poling on Bauhaus.
    - Sketch miscellaneous, undated (Box 55, Folder 11)
      Preface and Introduction to unidentified exhibition (Preface composed by Rudolf Wittkower).
    - Revue Illustree, undated (Box 55, Folder 12)
      Notes, correspondence, and photocopies. All materials related to Carl Martinez. Materials in French.
    - Notes, undated (Box 55, Folder 13)
      Notes about Royal Academy and sketches.
  - Freedom of Information Act [FBI Files], 1941-1968, 1988-2003
    Materials requested by Boime through the Freedom of Information Act. The subseries includes FBI files on a variety of artists (most suspected of Communist activities), all requested by Boime. Materials are filed alphabetically by artist's last name, with general materials at the end.
    - Charles Henry Alston, 1995 (Box 55, Folder 14)
      FBI Files on Charles Henry Alston requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - William Baziotes, 1989 (Box 55, Folder 15)
      FBI files on William Baziotes requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Thomas Hart Benton, 1990 (Box 55, Folder 16)
      FBI files on Thomas Hart Benton requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - David Burliuk, 1990 (Box 55, Folder 17)
      FBI files on David Burliuk requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - David Burliuk, 1991 (Box 55, Folder 18)
    - Aaron Douglas, 1996 (Box 56, Folder 1)
      FBI Files on Aaron Douglas requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Arshile Gorky, Adolph Gottlieb, and Mark Rothko, 1989 (Box 56, Folder 2)
      FBI Files on Arshile Gorky, Adolph Gottlieb, and Mark Rothko requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Clement Greenberg, 1998-2003 (Box 56, Folder 3)
      FBI files on Clement Greenberg requested through the Freedom of Information Act and correspondence.
    - Samuel (William) Gropper (1 of 2), undated (Box 56, Folder 4)
      FBI Files on Samuel Gropper (AKA William Gropper) requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Samuel (William) Gropper (2 of 2), undated (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - William Gropper, 1988 (Box 56, Folder 6)
      FBI files on William Gropper requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Norman Lewis, undated (Box 56, Folder 7)
      FBI files on Norman Lewis requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Rockwell Kent (1 of 5), 1949-1968 (Box 56, Folder 8)
      FBI files on Rockwell Kent requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Rockwell Kent (2 of 5), 1949-1968 (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Rockwell Kent (3 of 5), 1949-1968 (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - Rockwell Kent (4 of 5), 1949-1968 (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - Rockwell Kent (5 of 5), 1949-1968 (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - Rockwell Kent (1 of 4), 1941-1963 (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - Rockwell Kent (2 of 4), 1941-1963 (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - Rockwell Kent (4 of 4), 1941-1963 (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - Rockwell Kent (3 of 4), 1941-1963 (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - Rockwell Kent and Hale Aspacio Woodruff, 1992-1996 (Box 58, Folder 4)
      FBI files on Hale Aspacio Woodruff and Rockwell Kent requested through the Freedom of Information Act. Folder also includes correspondence and notes.
    - Yasuo Kuniyoshi, 1988 (Box 58, Folder 5)
      FBI files on Yasuo Kuniyoshi requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Lee Krasner Pollock and Meyer Schapiro, 1959-1963, 1997-2000 (Box 58, Folder 6)
      FBI files on Meyer Schapiro and Lee Krasner Pollock requested through the Freedom of Information Act and correspondence.
    - Adophe Reinhardt, 1990 (Box 58, Folder 7)
      FBI files on Adolph Reinhardt requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Leo Wilton on Reinhardt, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 1)
      Two drafts of paper by Boime's student Leo Wilton, "The FBI's Misuse of Power: A Case Study on Adolph Reinhardt", correspondence, and photocopied articles.
    - Boardman Robinson, 1989 (Box 59, Folder 2)
      FBI files on Boardman Robinson requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Harold Rosenburg (1 of 2), 2001 (Box 59, Folder 3)
      FBI files on Harold Rosenburg requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Harold Rosenburg (2 of 2), 2001 (Box 59, Folder 4)
    - Ben Shahn, 1990 (Box 59, Folder 5)
      FBI Files on Ben Shahn requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Moses Soyer, 1990 (Box 59, Folder 6)
      FBI Files on Moses Soyer requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Raphael Soyer, 1990 (Box 59, Folder 7)
      FBI files on Raphael Soyer requested through the Freedom of Information Act. See box 29 for additional research on Raphael Soyer.
    - Charles White, 1950-1964 (Box 59, Folder 8)
      FBI files on Charles White requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Richard Wright, 1942-1956 (Box 60, Folder 1)
      FBI files on Richard Wright requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Miscellaneous Freedom of Information Act files (1 of 2), 1984, 1988 (Box 60, Folder 2)
      Bulk of contents are FBI Files on Philip Evergood with some about Adolph Frederick Reinhardt. All materials were requested through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Miscellaneous Freedom of Information Act files (2 of 2), 1984, 1988 (Box 60, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Freedom of Information Act files, 1994 (Box 60, Folder 4)
      FBI Files on Rockwell Kent, Lee Krasner Pollock, Archibald Motley Jr., Dox Thrash, Louis Nevelson, and Isabel Bishop.
    - Freedom of Information Act miscellaneous, 1991-1994 (Box 60, Folder 5)
      Correspondence regarding FOIA requested files, file on Rockwell Kent, and photocopied articles.
    - FBI files (1 of 2), 1989 (Box 60, Folder 6)
      Correspondence with the FBI regarding requested files through the Freedom of Information Act. Files on Moses Soyer, Raphael Soyer, and David Smith.
    - FBI files (2 of 2), 1989 (Box 60, Folder 7)
    - FBI files, 1987-1992 (Box 61, Folder 1)
      FBI Files on Adolph Reinhardt, Samuel Gropper (AKA William Gropper), Stuart Davis, Alexander Calder, and correspondence.
    - FBI/CIA correspondence, bulk 1991, 1994 (Box 61, Folder 2)
      Correspondence with the CIA and FBI regarding requested artist files through the Freedom of Information Act.
    - Freedom of Information Act Correspondence, 1989 (Box 61, Folder 3)
      Correspondence with the FBI regarding requested Freedom of Information Act files. Folder also includes unidentified documents regarding Mark Rothko.
  - Art Movements, 1974-2002
    Materials relating to art movements, possibly for Boime's Social History of Modern Art series and other publications. The general art movements featured in this subseries are modernism, orientalism, neoclassicism, realism, impressionism, expressionism, Romanticism, symbolism, formalism, and genre painting. The subseries is arranged by art movement, beginning with the largest volume of material.
    - Primitive, ca. 1989-1990 (Box 139, Folder 8)
      Notes, pages from miscellaneous drafts (topics include African art, colonialism, Gauguin, Picasso, cubism, and Georges Braque), exhibition catalogs, and annotated lecture notes from Getty Lectures.
    - Romanticism seminar, 1990 (Box 139, Folder 9)
      Notes, correspondence from Clark Library, and attendance list for Art History 253.
    - Post-Colonialism, 1996 (Box 139, Folder 10)
      "Nonviolent Activist" newsletter, clippings, notes, and photocopies.
    - Modern primitive, 1976 (Box 61, Folder 4)
      Exhibition catalog from "Theater of the Object" at the Alternative Museum, notes, article by Wayne Andersen "Picasso and the Alien Oilcloth," and Heard Museum Gallery Guide and map.
    - Primitive, 1991-1992 (Box 61, Folder 5)
      Bibliography on physiognomy and phrenology, correspondence, photocopied articles, clippings, notes, PhD qualifying exam materials for Susan Masuoka, and syllabi for seminar "Primitivism and Art" offered by Cecilia Klein.
    - Cubism - origins, 1983, 1993 (Box 61, Folder 6)
      Lecture "Cubist Critics: Riviere and Metzinger" (authorship unclear), correspondence, and photocopied articles.
    - Futurists, 1996 (Box 61, Folder 7)